<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<recipes>
<recipe id="1">
  <title>Tapang Taal</title>
   <category>Breakfast</category>
  <prepTime>1 hour (plus marinating time)</prepTime>
  <ingredients>
    <item>500g pork loin or kasim, thinly sliced</item>
    <item>1/4 cup soy sauce</item>
    <item>1/4 cup vinegar</item>
    <item>6 cloves garlic, minced</item>
    <item>1 tbsp brown sugar</item>
    <item>1 tsp ground black pepper</item>
    <item>1 tsp salt</item>
    <item>Cooking oil for frying</item>
  </ingredients>
  <instructions>
    <step>In a bowl, combine soy sauce, vinegar, garlic, sugar, pepper, and salt to make the marinade.</step>
    <step>Add pork slices and mix well. Cover and marinate for at least 4 hours or overnight in the refrigerator.</step>
    <step>Heat oil in a pan over medium heat. Fry marinated pork slices until browned and cooked through.</step>
    <step>Serve hot with garlic fried rice and fried egg for a complete meal.</step>
  </instructions>
  <image>assets/images/tapang_taal.png</image>
</recipe>
<recipe id="2">
  <title>Longganisang Taal</title>
  <category>Breakfast</category>
  <prepTime>1 hour (plus marinating time)</prepTime>
  <ingredients>
    <item>1 kg ground pork (with fat)</item>
    <item>1 tbsp coarse salt</item>
    <item>1 tbsp brown sugar</item>
    <item>1 tbsp vinegar</item>
    <item>1 tbsp soy sauce</item>
    <item>1 tbsp ground black pepper</item>
    <item>1 head garlic, minced</item>
    <item>Sausage casings (optional)</item>
    <item>Water and oil for cooking</item>
  </ingredients>
  <instructions>
    <step>In a large bowl, mix ground pork with salt, sugar, vinegar, soy sauce, pepper, and garlic until well combined.</step>
    <step>Cover and let marinate in the refrigerator for at least 24 hours.</step>
    <step>If using casings, stuff the mixture into cleaned sausage casings and twist into links. Otherwise, shape into patties or leave loose.</step>
    <step>To cook, add a bit of water to a pan with the longganisa. Simmer until water evaporates, then fry in its own fat or a little oil until browned.</step>
    <step>Serve hot with garlic fried rice and egg (longsilog).</step>
  </instructions>
  <image>resources/longganisang_taal.png</image>
</recipe>
<recipe id="3">
  <title>Gotong Batangas</title>
   <category>Breakfast</category>
  <prepTime>2 hours</prepTime>
  <ingredients>
    <item>1 kg beef tripe (tuwalya), cleaned and cut into strips</item>
    <item>500g beef (kenchi or brisket), sliced</item>
    <item>1 medium onion, chopped</item>
    <item>6 cloves garlic, minced</item>
    <item>1 thumb-sized ginger, sliced</item>
    <item>1/4 cup annatto oil (atsuete oil)</item>
    <item>8 cups water or beef broth</item>
    <item>1 tbsp fish sauce (patis)</item>
    <item>Salt and pepper to taste</item>
    <item>Calamansi or vinegar for serving</item>
  </ingredients>
  <instructions>
    <step>In a large pot, sauté garlic, onion, and ginger in annatto oil until fragrant.</step>
    <step>Add the beef and tripe. Cook until lightly browned.</step>
    <step>Pour in water or beef broth. Bring to a boil, then lower heat and simmer until meat and tripe are tender (about 1.5 to 2 hours).</step>
    <step>Season with fish sauce, salt, and pepper to taste.</step>
    <step>Serve hot with steamed rice and calamansi or vinegar on the side.</step>
  </instructions>
  <image>assets/images/gotong_batangas.png</image>
</recipe>
<recipe id="4">
  <title>Lomi Batangas</title>
   <category>Breakfast</category>
  <prepTime>1 hour</prepTime>
  <ingredients>
    <item>500g fresh miki noodles (thick egg noodles)</item>
    <item>300g pork belly or pork kasim, sliced thinly</item>
    <item>100g pork liver, sliced</item>
    <item>1 egg, beaten</item>
    <item>1 medium onion, chopped</item>
    <item>4 cloves garlic, minced</item>
    <item>1 tbsp soy sauce</item>
    <item>1 tbsp fish sauce (patis)</item>
    <item>4 cups pork or chicken broth</item>
    <item>1 tbsp cornstarch mixed with 2 tbsp water (slurry)</item>
    <item>Salt and pepper to taste</item>
    <item>Cooking oil</item>
    <item>Chicharon, fried garlic, and spring onions for garnish</item>
  </ingredients>
  <instructions>
    <step>Heat oil in a pan. Sauté garlic and onion until fragrant.</step>
    <step>Add pork belly and cook until lightly browned. Add liver and cook briefly.</step>
    <step>Season with soy sauce, fish sauce, salt, and pepper.</step>
    <step>Pour in the broth and bring to a boil. Simmer for 10-15 minutes.</step>
    <step>Add the miki noodles and cook for another 5 minutes.</step>
    <step>Pour in the cornstarch slurry while stirring to thicken the soup.</step>
    <step>Slowly add the beaten egg while stirring to create egg strands.</step>
    <step>Top with chicharon, fried garlic, and spring onions before serving. Serve hot.</step>
  </instructions>
  <image>assets/images/lomi_batangas.png</image>
</recipe>
<recipe id="5">
  <title>Daing na Bangus</title>
  <category>Breakfast</category>
  <prepTime>1 hour (plus marinating time)</prepTime>
  <ingredients>
    <item>1 whole bangus (milkfish), butterflied and cleaned</item>
    <item>1/2 cup vinegar</item>
    <item>6 cloves garlic, crushed</item>
    <item>1 tsp ground black pepper</item>
    <item>1 tsp salt</item>
    <item>Cooking oil for frying</item>
  </ingredients>
  <instructions>
    <step>In a bowl, mix vinegar, garlic, pepper, and salt to make the marinade.</step>
    <step>Place the bangus in a shallow dish or ziplock bag and pour in the marinade. Marinate for at least 4 hours or overnight in the refrigerator.</step>
    <step>Drain the bangus and pat dry.</step>
    <step>Heat oil in a pan over medium heat. Fry the bangus skin-side down first until golden brown and crispy. Flip and cook the other side.</step>
    <step>Serve hot with garlic fried rice and egg (bangsilog), and a side of sliced tomatoes or spiced vinegar.</step>
  </instructions>
  <image>assets/images/daing_na_bangus.png</image>
</recipe>
<recipe id="6">
  <title>Pandesal at Kapeng Barako</title>
  <category>Breakfast</category>
  <prepTime>20 mins (for serving only)</prepTime>
  <ingredients>
    <item>6 pcs fresh pandesal (Filipino bread rolls)</item>
    <item>1 cup kapeng barako (Batangas coffee), freshly brewed</item>
    <item>Butter, cheese, or jam (optional spread for pandesal)</item>
    <item>Condensed milk or sugar (optional, for coffee)</item>
  </ingredients>
  <instructions>
    <step>Warm the pandesal in an oven or toaster for a few minutes, if desired.</step>
    <step>Brew kapeng barako using a coffee press, percolator, or traditional cloth strainer (katsa).</step>
    <step>Serve the warm pandesal with your choice of spread like butter, cheese, or jam.</step>
    <step>Serve kapeng barako black or sweetened with sugar or condensed milk, according to taste.</step>
    <step>Enjoy this classic Filipino breakfast pairing hot.</step>
  </instructions>
  <image>assets/images/pandesal_kapeng_barako.png</image>
</recipe>
<recipe id="7">
  <title>Pritong Tawilis</title>
  <category>Breakfast</category>
  <prepTime>25 mins</prepTime>
  <ingredients>
    <item>6 pcs fresh tawilis (freshwater sardines), cleaned and scaled</item>
    <item>1/2 tsp salt</item>
    <item>1/4 tsp ground black pepper</item>
    <item>1/2 cup all-purpose flour (optional, for light coating)</item>
    <item>Cooking oil for deep frying</item>
    <item>Vinegar with garlic and chili (for dipping)</item>
  </ingredients>
  <instructions>
    <step>Rinse the tawilis thoroughly and pat dry with paper towels.</step>
    <step>Season with salt and pepper. Optional: Lightly coat with flour for extra crispiness.</step>
    <step>Heat oil in a deep pan over medium-high heat.</step>
    <step>Fry the tawilis in batches until golden brown and crispy, about 3-5 minutes per side.</step>
    <step>Drain on paper towels to remove excess oil.</step>
    <step>Serve hot with vinegar dipping sauce and steamed rice.</step>
  </instructions>
  <image>assets/images/pritong_tawilis.png</image>
</recipe>
<recipe id="8">
  <title>Champorado with Tuyo</title>
 <category>Breakfast</category>
  <prepTime>45 mins</prepTime>
  <ingredients>
    <item>1 cup glutinous rice (malagkit)</item>
    <item>4 cups water</item>
    <item>1/2 cup tablea (pure cacao tablets) or 1/4 cup cocoa powder</item>
    <item>1/2 cup sugar (adjust to taste)</item>
    <item>1/4 tsp salt</item>
    <item>Evaporated or condensed milk for topping</item>
    <item>3–4 pcs tuyo (dried fish), fried</item>
  </ingredients>
  <instructions>
    <step>In a pot, bring water to a boil. Add glutinous rice and cook over medium heat, stirring occasionally to prevent sticking.</step>
    <step>Once the rice begins to soften, add tablea or cocoa powder. Stir until fully dissolved and well mixed.</step>
    <step>Add sugar and a pinch of salt. Simmer until the mixture thickens and rice is fully cooked.</step>
    <step>Adjust sweetness to taste, then remove from heat.</step>
    <step>In a separate pan, fry tuyo until crispy. Remove scales and bones if desired.</step>
    <step>Serve champorado hot in bowls, topped with milk and paired with fried tuyo on the side.</step>
  </instructions>
  <image>assets/images/champorado_with_tuyo.png</image>
</recipe>
<recipe id="9">
  <title>Suman sa Lihiya with Latik</title>
  <category>Breakfast</category>
  <prepTime>2 hours</prepTime>
  <ingredients>
    <item>2 cups glutinous rice (malagkit), soaked for 2 hours and drained</item>
    <item>1 tsp lihiya (lye water)</item>
    <item>Banana leaves, wilted and cut into wrapping-size pieces</item>
    <item>Cotton string or kitchen twine</item>
    <item>Water for boiling</item>
    <item>1 cup coconut cream (for latik)</item>
    <item>1/2 cup sugar (optional, for serving)</item>
  </ingredients>
  <instructions>
    <step>In a mixing bowl, combine soaked glutinous rice and lihiya. Mix until rice is evenly coated.</step>
    <step>Scoop 2–3 tablespoons of the mixture and place in the center of a banana leaf. Shape into a log and wrap tightly. Tie with string to secure.</step>
    <step>Place the wrapped suman in a large pot. Add enough water to cover and boil for 1.5 to 2 hours or until cooked and tender.</step>
    <step>Meanwhile, in a separate pan, simmer coconut cream over medium heat until oil separates and golden brown latik forms. Stir occasionally to prevent burning. Set aside.</step>
    <step>Once suman is cooked, let it cool slightly. Serve with latik and sugar on top, if desired.</step>
  </instructions>
  <image>assets/images/suman_sa_lihiya.png</image>
</recipe>
<recipe id="10">
  <title>Pinindot</title>
  <category>Breakfast</category>
  <prepTime>1 hour</prepTime>
  <ingredients>
    <item>1 cup glutinous rice flour</item>
    <item>1/2 cup water (for making bilo-bilo)</item>
    <item>2 cups coconut milk</item>
    <item>1 cup coconut cream (kakang gata)</item>
    <item>1 cup saba bananas, sliced</item>
    <item>1 cup sweet potatoes, cubed</item>
    <item>1 cup cooked sago (tapioca pearls)</item>
    <item>1 cup jackfruit (langka), sliced thinly</item>
    <item>1/2 cup sugar (adjust to taste)</item>
    <item>1/4 tsp salt</item>
  </ingredients>
  <instructions>
    <step>In a bowl, combine glutinous rice flour and water to form a soft dough. Roll into small balls to make bilo-bilo.</step>
    <step>In a pot, combine coconut milk and sugar. Bring to a gentle boil over medium heat.</step>
    <step>Add sweet potatoes and cook until halfway tender.</step>
    <step>Add bananas and jackfruit. Simmer for another 5 minutes.</step>
    <step>Gently drop in the rice balls (bilo-bilo) and cook until they float, about 5–7 minutes.</step>
    <step>Stir in cooked sago and coconut cream. Add salt and adjust sweetness as needed. Simmer for another 5 minutes.</step>
    <step>Serve warm in bowls as a comforting merienda or dessert.</step>
  </instructions>
  <image>assets/images/pinindot.png</image>
</recipe>
<recipe id="11">
  <title>Bulalo Batangas</title>
  <category>Lunch</category>
  <prepTime>3 hours</prepTime>
  <ingredients>
    <item>1.5 kg beef shank with bone marrow</item>
    <item>1 large corn on the cob, cut into chunks</item>
    <item>1 small cabbage, quartered</item>
    <item>1 large onion, quartered</item>
    <item>6 cloves garlic, crushed</item>
    <item>10 cups water</item>
    <item>2 tbsp fish sauce (patis)</item>
    <item>Salt and pepper to taste</item>
    <item>Green onions and peppercorns for garnish</item>
  </ingredients>
  <instructions>
    <step>In a large pot, combine beef shank, onion, garlic, and water. Bring to a boil and then simmer for 2–3 hours or until meat is tender.</step>
    <step>Skim off any scum that forms on the surface while cooking.</step>
    <step>Add corn and simmer for another 30 minutes until corn is tender.</step>
    <step>Add cabbage and cook for 5–7 minutes until just tender.</step>
    <step>Season broth with fish sauce, salt, and pepper.</step>
    <step>Serve hot, garnished with chopped green onions and whole peppercorns.</step>
  </instructions>
  <image>assets/images/bulalo_batangas.png</image>
</recipe>
<recipe id="12">
  <title>Sinaing na Tulingan</title>
   <category>Lunch</category>
  <prepTime>3 hours</prepTime>
  <ingredients>
    <item>1 kg tulingan (mackerel tuna), cleaned and gutted</item>
    <item>1/2 cup rock salt</item>
    <item>2 cups water</item>
    <item>2–3 pieces dried bay leaves (optional)</item>
    <item>Banana leaves (for wrapping)</item>
    <item>1 thumb-sized ginger, sliced (optional)</item>
  </ingredients>
  <instructions>
    <step>Layer banana leaves at the bottom of a pot.</step>
    <step>Place the tulingan fish inside the pot. Sprinkle salt evenly over the fish.</step>
    <step>Add water and bay leaves (and ginger if using).</step>
    <step>Cover the pot and simmer over low heat for about 2 to 3 hours, allowing the fish to cook slowly and absorb the flavors.</step>
    <step>Check occasionally to ensure there is enough liquid to prevent burning, adding more water if necessary.</step>
    <step>Serve hot with steamed rice and dipping vinegar.</step>
  </instructions>
  <image>assets/images/sinaing_na_tulingan.png</image>
</recipe>
<recipe id="13">
  <title>Adobo sa Dilaw</title>
 <category>Lunch</category>
  <prepTime>1 hour</prepTime>
  <ingredients>
    <item>1 kg pork belly or chicken, cut into serving pieces</item>
    <item>1/4 cup vinegar</item>
    <item>1/4 cup soy sauce</item>
    <item>1 cup coconut milk</item>
    <item>1 thumb-sized turmeric (luyang dilaw), grated or sliced</item>
    <item>6 cloves garlic, crushed</item>
    <item>2 bay leaves</item>
    <item>1 tsp black peppercorns</item>
    <item>1 tbsp cooking oil</item>
    <item>Salt to taste</item>
  </ingredients>
  <instructions>
    <step>Heat oil in a pot. Sauté garlic and turmeric until fragrant.</step>
    <step>Add pork or chicken pieces and brown on all sides.</step>
    <step>Pour in vinegar, soy sauce, coconut milk, bay leaves, and peppercorns. Do not stir immediately.</step>
    <step>Bring to a boil, then lower heat and simmer for 30-40 minutes or until meat is tender.</step>
    <step>Season with salt to taste. If sauce is too thin, simmer uncovered to reduce.</step>
    <step>Serve hot with steamed rice.</step>
  </instructions>
  <image>assets/images/adobo_sa_dilaw.png</image>
</recipe>
<recipe id="14">
  <title>Kalderetang Batangas</title>
   <category>Lunch</category>
  <prepTime>2 hours</prepTime>
  <ingredients>
    <item>1 kg beef chuck or brisket, cut into cubes</item>
    <item>2 medium potatoes, peeled and quartered</item>
    <item>2 medium carrots, peeled and sliced</item>
    <item>1 large onion, chopped</item>
    <item>4 cloves garlic, minced</item>
    <item>1 cup tomato sauce</item>
    <item>1/4 cup liver spread or pâté</item>
    <item>1 cup green peas</item>
    <item>2 cups beef broth or water</item>
    <item>1/4 cup soy sauce</item>
    <item>2 tbsp cooking oil</item>
    <item>Salt and pepper to taste</item>
    <item>1 bay leaf</item>
  </ingredients>
  <instructions>
    <step>Heat oil in a pot. Sauté garlic and onion until fragrant.</step>
    <step>Add beef cubes and brown on all sides.</step>
    <step>Pour in soy sauce and cook for 2 minutes.</step>
    <step>Add tomato sauce, beef broth, and bay leaf. Bring to a boil, then simmer covered for 1.5 to 2 hours or until beef is tender.</step>
    <step>Add potatoes, carrots, liver spread, and green peas. Cook until vegetables are tender and sauce thickens.</step>
    <step>Season with salt and pepper to taste. Remove bay leaf before serving.</step>
    <step>Serve hot with steamed rice.</step>
  </instructions>
  <image>assets/images/kalderetang_batangas.png</image>
</recipe>
<recipe id="15">
  <title>Tinolang Tadyang ng Baka</title>
   <category>Lunch</category>
  <prepTime>2 hours</prepTime>
  <ingredients>
    <item>1 kg beef short ribs (tadyang ng baka), cut into serving pieces</item>
    <item>1 medium green papaya or chayote, peeled and sliced</item>
    <item>1 bunch chili leaves (or malunggay leaves as substitute)</item>
    <item>1 medium onion, quartered</item>
    <item>4 cloves garlic, crushed</item>
    <item>1 thumb-sized ginger, sliced</item>
    <item>8 cups water</item>
    <item>2 tbsp fish sauce (patis)</item>
    <item>Salt and pepper to taste</item>
    <item>Cooking oil</item>
  </ingredients>
  <instructions>
    <step>Heat oil in a large pot. Sauté garlic, onion, and ginger until fragrant.</step>
    <step>Add beef ribs and brown slightly.</step>
    <step>Pour in water and bring to a boil. Lower heat and simmer for 1.5 to 2 hours or until meat is tender.</step>
    <step>Add fish sauce, salt, and pepper.</step>
    <step>Add green papaya or chayote and cook until tender.</step>
    <step>Stir in chili leaves just before turning off the heat.</step>
    <step>Serve hot with steamed rice.</step>
  </instructions>
  <image>assets/images/tinolang_tadyang_ng_baka.png</image>
</recipe>
<recipe id="16">
  <title>Ginisang Monggo</title>
   <category>Lunch</category>
  <prepTime>45 mins</prepTime>
  <ingredients>
    <item>1 cup mung beans (monggo), rinsed</item>
    <item>4 cups water or pork broth</item>
    <item>150g pork belly or pork shoulder, diced</item>
    <item>4 cloves garlic, minced</item>
    <item>1 medium onion, chopped</item>
    <item>2 medium tomatoes, chopped</item>
    <item>1 cup spinach or moringa leaves (malunggay)</item>
    <item>2 tbsp fish sauce (patis)</item>
    <item>Salt and pepper to taste</item>
    <item>Cooking oil</item>
  </ingredients>
  <instructions>
    <step>In a pot, boil mung beans in water or pork broth until soft, about 30-40 minutes. Mash slightly if desired.</step>
    <step>In a separate pan, heat oil and sauté garlic, onion, and tomatoes until fragrant and softened.</step>
    <step>Add pork and cook until browned.</step>
    <step>Pour sautéed mixture into the pot with mung beans. Stir well.</step>
    <step>Add fish sauce, salt, and pepper. Simmer for another 10 minutes.</step>
    <step>Add spinach or moringa leaves and cook until wilted.</step>
    <step>Serve hot with steamed rice.</step>
  </instructions>
  <image>assets/images/ginisang_monggo.png</image>
</recipe>
<recipe id="17">
  <title>Tinumis</title>
   <category>Lunch</category>
  <prepTime>1 hour</prepTime>
  <ingredients>
    <item>500g pork shoulder, cut into cubes</item>
    <item>1 cup pork blood</item>
    <item>1 medium onion, chopped</item>
    <item>4 cloves garlic, minced</item>
    <item>2 tbsp fish sauce (patis)</item>
    <item>1/2 cup vinegar</item>
    <item>1 tbsp cooking oil</item>
    <item>2 cups water</item>
    <item>Salt and pepper to taste</item>
    <item>Optional: chili peppers for spice</item>
  </ingredients>
  <instructions>
    <step>Heat oil in a pot and sauté garlic and onion until fragrant.</step>
    <step>Add pork and cook until browned.</step>
    <step>Pour in vinegar and allow to simmer for a few minutes without stirring.</step>
    <step>Add water and fish sauce, then simmer until pork is tender, about 30 minutes.</step>
    <step>Slowly pour in pork blood while stirring gently to prevent curdling.</step>
    <step>Season with salt, pepper, and optional chili peppers.</step>
    <step>Simmer for another 10 minutes until the blood thickens and the flavors meld.</step>
    <step>Serve hot with steamed rice.</step>
  </instructions>
  <image>assets/images/tinumis.png</image>
</recipe>
<recipe id="18">
  <title>Inihaw na Tilapia sa Gata</title>
  <category>Lunch</category>
  <prepTime>1 hour</prepTime>
  <ingredients>
    <item>2 whole tilapia, cleaned and scaled</item>
    <item>1 cup coconut milk</item>
    <item>4 cloves garlic, minced</item>
    <item>1 thumb-sized ginger, sliced</item>
    <item>2 pieces long chili (siling haba), sliced</item>
    <item>1 medium onion, sliced</item>
    <item>2 tbsp fish sauce (patis)</item>
    <item>Salt and pepper to taste</item>
    <item>Banana leaves or foil for grilling</item>
  </ingredients>
  <instructions>
    <step>Make diagonal slashes on the tilapia to allow marinade to penetrate.</step>
    <step>In a bowl, mix coconut milk, garlic, ginger, onion, chili, fish sauce, salt, and pepper.</step>
    <step>Marinate the tilapia in the coconut milk mixture for at least 30 minutes.</step>
    <step>Preheat the grill. Wrap each tilapia in banana leaves or aluminum foil.</step>
    <step>Grill the fish over medium heat for about 20-25 minutes, turning occasionally, until cooked through and slightly charred.</step>
    <step>Serve hot with steamed rice and drizzle with remaining coconut sauce.</step>
  </instructions>
  <image>assets/images/inihaw_na_tilapia_sa_gata.png</image>
</recipe>
<recipe id="19">
  <title>Kari-karing Baka</title>
  <category>Lunch</category>
  <prepTime>2 hours</prepTime>
  <ingredients>
    <item>1 kg beef brisket or shank, cut into cubes</item>
    <item>2 cups peanut butter or ground peanuts</item>
    <item>1 cup cooked kidney beans (or garbanzo beans)</item>
    <item>1 medium eggplant, sliced</item>
    <item>1 cup string beans (sitaw), cut into 2-inch pieces</item>
    <item>4 cloves garlic, minced</item>
    <item>1 large onion, chopped</item>
    <item>2 tbsp cooking oil</item>
    <item>4 cups beef broth or water</item>
    <item>2 tbsp annatto powder (achuete) dissolved in 1/4 cup water</item>
    <item>2 tbsp fish sauce (patis)</item>
    <item>Salt and pepper to taste</item>
    <item>1-2 pieces bay leaves</item>
  </ingredients>
  <instructions>
    <step>Heat oil in a pot. Sauté garlic and onion until fragrant.</step>
    <step>Add beef cubes and brown on all sides.</step>
    <step>Add beef broth, bay leaves, and simmer until beef is tender, about 1.5 to 2 hours.</step>
    <step>Stir in peanut butter and annatto water. Mix well to create the sauce.</step>
    <step>Add kidney beans, eggplant, and string beans. Cook until vegetables are tender.</step>
    <step>Season with fish sauce, salt, and pepper to taste.</step>
    <step>Simmer for another 10 minutes to blend flavors.</step>
    <step>Serve hot with steamed rice.</step>
  </instructions>
  <image>assets/images/kari-karing_baka.png</image>
</recipe>
<recipe id="20">
  <title>Laing Batangas</title>
  <category>Lunch</category>
  <prepTime>1 hour 30 mins</prepTime>
  <ingredients>
    <item>500g dried taro leaves (dahon ng gabi), washed and drained</item>
    <item>2 cups coconut milk (kakang gata)</item>
    <item>1 cup coconut cream (kakang gata), thick</item>
    <item>200g pork belly, sliced thinly</item>
    <item>6 cloves garlic, minced</item>
    <item>1 large onion, chopped</item>
    <item>2 thumb-sized ginger, sliced</item>
    <item>4 pieces dried red chili peppers (siling labuyo)</item>
    <item>2 tbsp shrimp paste (bagoong alamang)</item>
    <item>Salt to taste</item>
    <item>Cooking oil</item>
  </ingredients>
  <instructions>
    <step>Heat oil in a pan and sauté garlic, onion, and ginger until fragrant.</step>
    <step>Add pork belly and cook until browned.</step>
    <step>Pour in shrimp paste and cook for 2 minutes.</step>
    <step>Add coconut milk and bring to a gentle simmer.</step>
    <step>Layer taro leaves on top without stirring. Cover and cook on low heat for 20 minutes.</step>
    <step>Pour in coconut cream and add dried chili peppers. Stir gently to combine.</step>
    <step>Continue cooking on low heat for another 30-40 minutes until leaves are tender and sauce thickens. Stir occasionally to prevent sticking.</step>
    <step>Season with salt to taste. Serve hot with steamed rice.</step>
  </instructions>
  <image>assets/images/laing_batangas.png</image>
</recipe>
<recipe id="21">
  <title>Nilagang Baka</title>
  <category>Dinner</category>
  <prepTime>2 hours</prepTime>
  <ingredients>
    <item>1 kg beef shank or brisket, cut into chunks</item>
    <item>1 large onion, quartered</item>
    <item>5 cloves garlic, crushed</item>
    <item>6 cups water</item>
    <item>2 medium potatoes, peeled and quartered</item>
    <item>2 ears corn, cut into thirds</item>
    <item>1 small cabbage, quartered</item>
    <item>1 bunch green beans, trimmed</item>
    <item>Salt and pepper to taste</item>
  </ingredients>
  <instructions>
    <step>In a large pot, combine beef, onion, garlic, and water. Bring to a boil, then reduce heat and simmer for 1.5 to 2 hours until beef is tender.</step>
    <step>Add potatoes and corn to the pot. Cook until vegetables are tender, about 15 minutes.</step>
    <step>Add cabbage and green beans. Cook for another 5-7 minutes until vegetables are just cooked.</step>
    <step>Season with salt and pepper to taste. Serve hot with steamed rice and a side of fish sauce with calamansi (optional).</step>
  </instructions>
  <image>assets/images/nilagang_baka.png</image>
</recipe>
<recipe id="22">
  <title>Paksiw na Galunggong</title>
  <category>Dinner</category>
  <prepTime>45 mins</prepTime>
  <ingredients>
    <item>6 pcs galunggong (round scad fish), cleaned and gutted</item>
    <item>1 cup vinegar</item>
    <item>1 cup water</item>
    <item>1 thumb-sized ginger, sliced</item>
    <item>5 cloves garlic, crushed</item>
    <item>2 pcs long green chili (siling haba)</item>
    <item>1 medium onion, sliced</item>
    <item>1 tbsp brown sugar</item>
    <item>Salt and pepper to taste</item>
  </ingredients>
  <instructions>
    <step>In a pot, combine vinegar, water, ginger, garlic, onion, and brown sugar. Bring to a boil.</step>
    <step>Add the galunggong fish carefully into the pot. Do not stir to avoid breaking the fish.</step>
    <step>Add the green chilies and season with salt and pepper.</step>
    <step>Simmer on low heat for about 20-25 minutes or until the fish is cooked and the sauce slightly reduces.</step>
    <step>Serve hot with steamed rice.</step>
  </instructions>
  <image>assets/images/paksiw_na_galunggong.png</image>
</recipe>
<recipe id="23">
  <title>Pritong Liempo</title>
  <category>Dinner</category>
  <prepTime>30 mins</prepTime>
  <ingredients>
    <item>500g pork belly (liempo), sliced into 1-inch thick pieces</item>
    <item>2 tsp salt</item>
    <item>1 tsp ground black pepper</item>
    <item>Cooking oil for frying</item>
  </ingredients>
  <instructions>
    <step>Season the pork belly slices with salt and pepper on both sides. Let it rest for 10 minutes.</step>
    <step>Heat enough cooking oil in a pan over medium heat.</step>
    <step>Fry the pork belly pieces until golden brown and crispy on both sides, about 6-8 minutes per side.</step>
    <step>Drain excess oil on paper towels and serve hot with steamed rice and dipping sauce like vinegar with garlic and chili.</step>
  </instructions>
  <image>assets/images/pritong_liempo.png</image>
</recipe>
<recipe id="24">
  <title>Sinampalukang Manok</title>
  <category>Dinner</category>
  <prepTime>1 hour</prepTime>
  <ingredients>
    <item>1 kg chicken, cut into serving pieces</item>
    <item>2 tablespoons cooking oil</item>
    <item>1 thumb-sized ginger, sliced into strips</item>
    <item>1 medium onion, chopped</item>
    <item>3 cloves garlic, minced</item>
    <item>2 medium tomatoes, chopped</item>
    <item>4 cups water</item>
    <item>1 cup young tamarind leaves (or spinach as substitute)</item>
    <item>1 packet sinigang mix or 1 cup fresh tamarind juice (optional, for added sourness)</item>
    <item>2 long green chilies (siling haba)</item>
    <item>Fish sauce (patis) or salt to taste</item>
  </ingredients>
  <instructions>
    <step>Heat oil in a pot. Sauté garlic, onion, ginger, and tomatoes until fragrant and softened.</step>
    <step>Add chicken pieces and cook until lightly browned.</step>
    <step>Pour in water and bring to a boil. Simmer until chicken is cooked through, about 30–40 minutes.</step>
    <step>Add tamarind leaves and green chilies. Let it simmer for another 5–10 minutes.</step>
    <step>Add sinigang mix or tamarind juice if a stronger sour flavor is desired. Season with fish sauce or salt to taste.</step>
    <step>Serve hot with steamed rice.</step>
  </instructions>
  <image>assets/images/sinampalukang_manok.png</image>
</recipe>
<recipe id="25">
  <title>Ginisang Puso ng Saging</title>
  <category>Dinner</category>
  <prepTime>45 minutes</prepTime>
  <ingredients>
    <item>1 medium banana blossom (puso ng saging), sliced thinly</item>
    <item>2 tablespoons salt (for soaking)</item>
    <item>2 tablespoons cooking oil</item>
    <item>3 cloves garlic, minced</item>
    <item>1 medium onion, chopped</item>
    <item>200 grams ground pork (optional)</item>
    <item>1 tablespoon fish sauce (patis)</item>
    <item>1/2 cup coconut milk (optional)</item>
    <item>Salt and pepper to taste</item>
  </ingredients>
  <instructions>
    <step>Peel and thinly slice the banana blossom. Rub with salt and soak in water for 15–20 minutes to remove bitterness. Squeeze and drain well.</step>
    <step>Heat oil in a pan. Sauté garlic and onion until fragrant.</step>
    <step>If using ground pork, add and cook until browned.</step>
    <step>Add the drained banana blossom and sauté for 5–7 minutes.</step>
    <step>Season with fish sauce, salt, and pepper. Stir well.</step>
    <step>If using coconut milk, pour it in and simmer for another 5 minutes until sauce is slightly reduced.</step>
    <step>Serve hot with steamed rice.</step>
  </instructions>
  <image>assets/images/ginisang_puso_ng_saging.png</image>
</recipe>
<recipe id="26">
  <title>Inihaw na Bangus</title>
  <category>Dinner</category>
  <prepTime>45 mins</prepTime>
  <ingredients>
    <item>1 whole bangus (milkfish), cleaned and butterflied</item>
    <item>3 cloves garlic, minced</item>
    <item>1 medium onion, chopped</item>
    <item>1 tomato, chopped</item>
    <item>2 tbsp soy sauce</item>
    <item>1 tbsp calamansi juice or lemon juice</item>
    <item>Salt and pepper to taste</item>
    <item>Banana leaves (optional, for grilling)</item>
  </ingredients>
  <instructions>
    <step>In a bowl, mix garlic, onion, tomato, soy sauce, calamansi juice, salt, and pepper to make the marinade.</step>
    <step>Stuff the marinade inside the butterflied bangus and let it marinate for at least 15 minutes.</step>
    <step>Wrap the fish with banana leaves if using, or place directly on the grill.</step>
    <step>Grill the fish over medium heat for about 20-25 minutes on each side or until cooked and slightly charred.</step>
    <step>Serve hot with steamed rice and dipping sauce (soy sauce with chili and calamansi).</step>
  </instructions>
  <image>assets/images/inihaw_na_bangus.png</image>
</recipe>
<recipe id="27">
  <title>Giniling na Baboy</title>
  <category>Dinner</category>
  <prepTime>40 mins</prepTime>
  <ingredients>
    <item>500g ground pork</item>
    <item>1 medium onion, chopped</item>
    <item>3 cloves garlic, minced</item>
    <item>1 medium tomato, chopped</item>
    <item>1 medium potato, peeled and diced</item>
    <item>1 medium carrot, peeled and diced</item>
    <item>1/2 cup green peas</item>
    <item>2 tbsp cooking oil</item>
    <item>2 tbsp soy sauce</item>
    <item>1 tbsp fish sauce (patis)</item>
    <item>Salt and pepper to taste</item>
  </ingredients>
  <instructions>
    <step>Heat oil in a pan over medium heat. Sauté onion, garlic, and tomato until fragrant.</step>
    <step>Add ground pork and cook until browned.</step>
    <step>Add potatoes, carrots, and green peas. Stir and cook for about 5 minutes.</step>
    <step>Season with soy sauce, fish sauce, salt, and pepper. Simmer until vegetables are tender and flavors meld.</step>
    <step>Serve hot with steamed rice.</step>
  </instructions>
  <image>assets/images/giniling_na_baboy.png</image>
</recipe>
<recipe id="28">
  <title>Itlog na Maalat</title>
  <category>Dinner</category>
  <prepTime>—</prepTime>
  <ingredients>
    <item>Salted duck eggs (itlog na maalat), store-bought or homemade</item>
  </ingredients>
  <instructions>
    <step>If raw, boil the salted duck eggs in water for about 10-12 minutes until cooked.</step>
    <step>Let the eggs cool, then peel the shells carefully.</step>
    <step>Serve sliced as a side dish or condiment, commonly paired with garlic fried rice (sinangag) or tomatoes.</step>
  </instructions>
  <image>assets/images/itlog_na_maalat.png</image>
</recipe>
<recipe id="29">
  <title>Tinapa with Rice</title>
  <category>Dinner</category>
  <prepTime>30 mins</prepTime>
  <ingredients>
    <item>2 pcs tinapa (smoked fish), cleaned and deboned</item>
    <item>4 cups cooked white rice</item>
    <item>4 cloves garlic, minced</item>
    <item>2 tbsp cooking oil</item>
    <item>Tomato slices (optional)</item>
    <item>Salt and pepper to taste</item>
  </ingredients>
  <instructions>
    <step>Heat oil in a pan and sauté garlic until golden and fragrant.</step>
    <step>Add flaked tinapa and cook for 2-3 minutes to heat through.</step>
    <step>Mix the sautéed tinapa with cooked rice, season with salt and pepper.</step>
    <step>Serve with sliced tomatoes on the side if desired.</step>
  </instructions>
  <image>assets/images/tinapa_with_rice.png</image>
</recipe>
<recipe id="30">
  <title>Igado</title>
  <category>Dinner</category>
  <prepTime>1 hour</prepTime>
  <ingredients>
    <item>500 grams pork tenderloin, sliced into strips</item>
    <item>250 grams pork liver, sliced into strips</item>
    <item>2 tablespoons vinegar</item>
    <item>2 tablespoons soy sauce</item>
    <item>3 cloves garlic, minced</item>
    <item>1 medium onion, chopped</item>
    <item>1 red bell pepper, sliced into strips</item>
    <item>1 green bell pepper, sliced into strips</item>
    <item>1 cup green peas (optional)</item>
    <item>2 tablespoons cooking oil</item>
    <item>Bay leaves (2-3 pieces)</item>
    <item>Salt and pepper to taste</item>
  </ingredients>
  <instructions>
    <step>Heat oil in a pan. Sauté garlic and onion until fragrant.</step>
    <step>Add pork tenderloin and cook until lightly browned.</step>
    <step>Pour in vinegar (do not stir) and let it boil for a few minutes to cook off the acidity.</step>
    <step>Add soy sauce, bay leaves, and season with salt and pepper. Let simmer until pork is tender.</step>
    <step>Add pork liver and cook for 5–7 minutes, stirring occasionally.</step>
    <step>Add bell peppers and green peas (if using). Cook for another 3–5 minutes or until vegetables are tender but still crisp.</step>
    <step>Adjust seasoning if needed. Serve hot with steamed rice.</step>
  </instructions>
  <image>assets/images/igado.png</image>
</recipe>
</recipes>